Hardin hug Johnson Melton row Mr
President flag United States
America
stand indivisible
good afternoon everyone please have a
seat last week marked the signing of
President Obama honoring the national
apprenticeship week and last week um was
the 10th anniversary that so let's honor
our apprentices and I would like to give
my phone number is my role is treasur of
the elal Federation of Labor if
anybody's interested in getting
connected to a building trade
you can reach me at
5525 I'll be glad to get you connected
to any of the Omaha Building Trades are
in need of good
workers with
the um Blue Collar boxing is tomorrow
with the theme of the
apprentices it's at the backer Arena
tomorrow we're Union building craft
members box each other with all the
proceeds going to the United Way of the
Midlands and the Nebraska Center for
Workforce Development and education it's
a great thing the unions do they train
by a good sanction trainer and they Spar
for three rounds it's a lot of fun if
you want to make it out you can also
call my office if you want to try to get
some tickets but it's at the backx arena
tomorrow at
7 and tomorrow or I guess Thursday it's
Thanksgiving I would like to wish
everybody a very Happy Thanksgiving week
and watch some football and eat some
good turkey and Pie and put on 10 pound
sounds like I probably will so Happy
Thanksgiving everybody thanks M
president thank you an Affidavit of
publication is on file for the
pre-council and city council meeting and
a current copy of the open meeting Act
is posted in a white binder on the East
wall of legislative Chambers good
afternoon welcome to the Omaha city
council we appreciate having you here
today look forward to hearing your
testimony on our many items I'd
encourage you to turn your cell phones
off or at least to vibrate if you have
difficulty hearing the proceedings today
you can see our building commission
attendant here uh for listening to
device or you may notice that we have
closed captioning in the back of the
back of the room as
well item six to consider a Class C lqu
license for Blue Hawaii located at 1303
South 72nd Street Suite 108 and I will
note this is actually a class eye
license um the application notice to
property owners and the public hearing
notice All State class ey it was just
listed on the agenda as a Class C so all
the supplemental information is correct
thank you for that
clarification the public hearing and
vote on number six is today we have the
applicant by Zoom we'll get you off mute
here in a
second all right go ahead name and
address
please um my name is Jen Don Pan um uh
Blue Hawaii Resturant located
13037 south um sorry 1303 South 72nd
Street site number 108 Omaha Nebraska
68124 great thank you are there any
other proponents that want to speak
today see none any
opponents public hearing is closed Mr
Bagley you're recognized thanks Mr
President good afternoon can you hear me
on the
zoom yes good afternoon just a quick
question what are the hours of operation
going to be for your business
eror um from mon um from Sunday to
Thursday we will be open 11: a.m. and
will'll be closed on 9 900 pm on the on
the weekend day uh Friday and Saturday
we open from 11 a.m. and then we close
at 9:30 p.m. okay thanks Mr President
I'll make a motion to approve this and I
wish you the best of luck out there in
zarbin welcome to aarin Second thanks Mr
President thank you there's a motion a
second to approve roll call Bagley
Hardin hug Johnson Melton row Mr
President yes motion pass 7 to zero item
seven to consider a class SE liquor
license for Darby's Tavern located at
6503 Sunshine Drive public hearing and
vote on number seven is today proponents
please uh my name is Tim kek legally
Paul T cry uh it's been in my family's
it's been my family's business for the
last 91 years uh my address is 7819
South 45th Avenue uh ZIP
68157 bill viw Raska great thank you any
other proponents today uh my wife is
with me as well all right uh this is
Rose cry we've been married 34 years we
have two children and I'm glad she's
always by my
side great thank you any other
proponents that want to
speak see none any
opponents public hearing Clos Mr hug
you're recognizing let make a motion to
approve I'll it thank you Amy motion to
approve in a second sounds like there
hasn't been any problems in 91 years
you're probably okay there's been
problems we we've survived but thank you
very much for your time and
consideration you bet motion a second to
approve roll call bagle Harding hug
Johnson Melton row Mr President yes
motion pass 7even to
zero item eight to consider a Class D
liquor license for Mega saver located at
8242 Maple Street public hearing and
vote on number eight is today proponents
please hi my name is Tamar samv here
with mega saver uh my address is 6440
Cedar Plaza
68816 okay thank you any other
proponents
today seeing none any
opponents public hearing is
closed a motion a second to approve roll
call Bagley Hardin hug Johnson Melton
row Mr President yes motion pass 7 to
zero than item nine to consider a Class
D liquor license for Redmond supermarket
located at 4205 Redmond Avenue public
hearing and vote on number nine is today
proponents please good afternoon Mr
President members of the council David
Howton here on behalf of the applicant
Redmond Supermarket LLC doing business
as Redmond Supermarket uh they're here
today they presently hold a Class B
liquor license and they're looking to
upgrade that license to a Class D
license uh the owner and proprietor of
the business is Tariq Ali who owns four
other sea stores and small supermarkets
in the community um the hours of
operation are 8 and 10 p.m. Monday
through Thursday and it's open till 11:
pm on Friday and Saturday um this store
has been operated with no incident for
the last two years and hence the request
uh for an upgraded license um if you
have any questions uh I'd be free to uh
answer anything I could and also my
client Mr Al is so here as well thank
you thank you any other proponents that
want to
speak see none any
opponents public hearings closed Miss
Johnson you're recognized thank you Mr
President um this area this community is
in very much need of Economics um on a
variety of levels um that could include
housing it could include businesses it
could include a number of things that
also
includes um having businesses such as
the gentleman that's in front of us um
however um the community is very much uh
against additional liquor
Licensing in the city of Omaha and North
Omaha more affectionately
because there is a grocery store
nearby and this area is a very poor
area and we're concerned about the
opportunity to always have liquor
license available to us as opposed to
having meaningful businesses such as car
washes uh
entertainment all of these things that
also make a community Thrive we're
lacking those things in this particular
particular
Community but unfortunately the powers
that be only gives us the opportunity to
have liquor license at a profounding
voice and that's somewhat concerning and
so my constituents are constantly uh
supporting the idea that yes we do want
to see more businesses but we'd like to
see other things other than a liquor
license and for that reason and I won't
be supporting that thank you thank you
Miss Melton you're recognized oh thank
you uh Mr can you come back
up um and while you're on your way up I
just want to note that this they already
have a liquor license and they've been
in business so we aren't approving a new
liquor license even if we denied this
today they get to keep the liquor
license they have and they will still be
continuing to sell alcohol is that
correct uh that's correct they have a
class B license right now which allows
them to sell beer but but not wine or
liquor they would stipulate to selling
no shooters we understand that that's
sometimes a concern in the North Omaha
Community um but
there I could I could go through the
Litany of things that he sells as a
convenience store you know including
milk eggs butter bacon eggs fruits and
vegetables all things the community
needs um but unfortunately to remain
competitive you have to have the ability
to sell everything that the guy down the
street or two block away cells and in
this case there are plenty of
competitors uh there are corporations
large corporations out of State
Corporations that have been awarded
these liquor licenses and right now we
have an owner that's in our community uh
that wants to remain competitive and
that's why it's asking for the upgrade
sure yeah and I just I thought it was
important to not we aren't passing a new
liquor license this is just allowing
them to sell more than beer if we deny
it today he can still continue to sell
beer he still continues to have a li
license that's correct okay
um and I think what I heard what we like
to see is and what's been very common is
to have no sales of single or package
container containers that are 50
milliliters or less of liquor I know we
we like to call them Shooters but to be
more specific um we it's 50 milliliters
or less and so your client would be
willing to stipulate that restriction
yes okay I I think that that would be
better so that we're not selling the
little Shooters we don't we really don't
want these stores to be refrigerators
for the neighborhood sure um but I
understand he already has the liquor
license also I think it's important that
we don't have a place that actually
sells milk bread I I think you even
mentioned that they sell some vegetables
and some fruits canned vegetables and
fruits um the things that they can keep
on the shelves okay uh potatoes Tomatoes
bananas are usually offered uh butter
bread eggs things you have in a store
with food the food desert that we have I
think um on the Eastern side of our town
um I think it's important that we also
make sure that stores that do offer the
food that they can afford to stay open
and I know with the inflationary rates
and the cost of food I'm sure those
profit margins are so small may not be
enough so I think with those
restrictions I would be
satisfied uh with that so I know there's
some others that may want to talk I
would like to make uh a motion to amend
this to restrict the sales no sales of
single or package containers 50
milliliters or less of liquor
I'll okay there's a motion in a second
to approve with those restrictions Mr
hug you're
recognized uh good afternoon are are
your clients here yeah Mr Al is here
today could could they come down I mean
you you you've kind of touched on the
other items they stock but I'd like him
to amplify a little more okay
okay hi good afternoon coming down I
have actually been in your store
probably not the last two years but
probably really close two years ago okay
um
I so I I I got a good idea of what's on
your shelves or what was on your shelves
two years ago um your attorney has made
some comments but could you go into
detail and tell us other than alcohol
and beer what's on your shelves sure uh
we sell like uh all type of groceries uh
we have petables uh like you mentioned
eggs cheese and milk um the all da
product uh we have a about I think eight
door freezer that carries a whole
variety of frozen food and we do have a
small sample of uh fruits and vegetables
the stuff that we could keep that cells
right away okay we do have so to just
soap yeah we have about four aisles of
household yeah groceries and what are
your hours uh 8:00 a.m. to 10 p.m. 8
a.m. 10 p.m. 7 days a week 11: p.m. on
Friday 11 p.m. yeah okay and uh do you
have any problems in your parking
lot nothing major no might have like a
here and there but nothing that concerns
us or we have to get security on I know
your neighborhood's in flux there's been
a lot of improvement up up the street
from you over the recent years right I
noticed it's been much better lately the
last couple years yeah it's definitely
been an improvement yes there is um is
there anything else that we haven't
asked that you'd like to tell
us no I mean I just want to get the
chance just to compete like any other
business pretty much okay
well I appreciate your entrepreneurship
and your commitment to the community to
provide the services and the opportunity
you do have thank thank you thank you
Miss Johnson yes I would like to thank
Miss Milton for pointing out that this
was a liquor license so my recent
conversation was not that there wasn't a
liquor license it was simply to point
out that there was going to be an
extended amount of liquor to be sold at
this location and the fact that this
area is in so much need of other things
other uh industry things that is needed
in order to make the community Thrive
but again I thank you for pointing out
that there is currently a liquor license
and that this is an extension of what he
is able to sell I also would like to uh
share or remind this body that just
under two years ago this was brought to
us and this liquor license was uh
recommended not to go any further I
don't see that much has changed
regarding those terms those conditions
in which we decided not to support it
nothing much has changed in this
community and the sentiments regarding
how or what this perceived is being
perceived in this community has changed
as it relates to the community the
community is not here today because they
feel as though that they wouldn't be
supported by the body so there would be
no point in coming and that's really sad
that we have residents and community
members in Omaha that feel like they
have no voice that they can't come here
and and and really State what their
desires what their wishes are and that
they feel that their voices are not
being heard that's really sad that we
have a community like that in the city
of Omaha especially and we're try we're
trying to thrive to encourage Young
Folks to remain in this
area thank you thank you Mr bigley
thanks Mr President David couple quick
questions for
you good afternoon if I recall correctly
was it maybe in on or about in June of
2023 when they got the original license
I believe that's correct yes have they
had any issues with 911 or getting cited
for any selling to miners or any other
infractions or violations with the omal
police department no violations so far
as I'm aware I think Mr could confirm
that and looking back in my notes at
that time what was the investment I
don't was it a couple $1,000 that was
invested he's made about $200,000 worth
of a capital investment in the property
um currently he has four
employees um and
you know the unfortunate part of the
small grocery business is that if if
certain businesses down the street can
sell it and we're
excluding um other
businesses it it makes them less
competitive in the marketplace so I mean
really this is an issue this is an issue
from him to bring in business and to
keep business and a locally owned
business in the neighborhood and if
apologies if this is repetitive but at
the time back in the summer of 23 when
we approved the original license there
was produce and there was milk and eggs
and bread that were being sold cheese is
that still the case it is still the case
yes okay thanks David thanks Mr
President thank you Mr hardy thank you
Mr President um Dave I'll just have you
stand there for a minute I might have
one or two questions but um I want to
make sure I need to ask the court this I
don't believe this body has was um
insinuated uh earlier that this body did
not turn down the original liquor
license application is that correct
Madam clerk um that is correct so I
pulled up the recommendation and the
motion was to approve as amended to
amend it from a Class D liquor license
to a class B license right okay thank
you and I think the the conversation at
the time too was let's get a little air
underneath the wings and and see how we
did and and I don't think as I'm on the
law committee for almost the past two
years and I don't think there have been
any um Tavern reports associated with
this location that's which is which is a
good sign um and I know that that you
and your client have talked to some of
the not only the neighbors but the
neighboring
businesses um in addition to the daycare
center which I think actually uh sent a
letter um supportive of Mr Ali and his
business sec correct that's correct okay
all right thank you thank you thank you
Miss Johnson uh I still would ask the
question what is change from the last
time when this was brought to our
attention we approved the class B and
now we're trying to extend it what is
the difference and that's what the
community wants to know what is the
difference is that a question to us M
councilwoman yes what is the difference
I think it's the track record right when
they initially went for the class D
license and a Class B was awarded um it
was essentially a negotiation because we
need to find out how this particular
business owner operates and over the
last two years he's proved to be a
responsible operator and I think I think
that's the difference from our
perspective so what type of controls are
we U willing to do um to
ensure that the concerns that the
community
has um is
heard um in other words we two years ago
three years ago um we needed him to have
a track record and now we believe him to
have demonstrated that and and we're all
business individuals we know that once
something happens um we need to still
put controls in place to ensure that
what we want to um have as an expected
outcome that it remains as such what
things are we going to put in place to
ensure that that behavior will continue
if we were to extend this um well
obviously I think to the extent he can
he s uh regulates his own business and
Mak sure he's operating in the way he
has been Opera operating it um but I
think uh his agreement to stipulate not
to sell what a regular class D license
uh holder could sell is is a good faith
effort to um try to address some of the
concerns that may have been brought to
your office so is your client willing to
um um attend some of the neighborhood
meetings to um develop and continue to
nurture relationships in that Community
as a business owner um I wouldn't speak
for him about joining the neighborhood
association but I assume that all that
he would want to do all of that is that
correct yeah I mean I think it makes
sense for his business to be a part of
the community for sure thank you
yep thank you Mr hardy yeah I was just
going to say I think to answer maybe
part of the question that was posed is
that um if if the operator does not
operate within the um the Norms of of
what the the rules and
regulations his liquor license would be
taken away so I don't think we go into
each and every U situation assuming the
worst out possible outcome we want to
give every opportunity he's he's got a
proven track record give him the
opportunity if if and I don't have any
question that he's not going to be
successful and continue to run a good
operation but if that changes there are
repercussions for that and he will be
subject to those so that's that's the
answer to that question and again and
talking
about and I I'm sure I'm guilty of this
too but to to generalize the community I
just brought up an example of you know
the the neighboring daycare center
sending a letter of support for this man
and his business so they're part of the
community so I I don't necessarily think
we can generalize to say the community
as a whole doesn't want this because I
think there are some in the community
that do want
this I would agree and I'd fully
stipulate at the rate of saying too much
we've reached out to the neighborhood
association president and her comment
back she hears some of the same concerns
Miss Johnson does so um Mrs moss on
behalf of the neighborhood association
her official position in an email to me
is neutral rather not in support or
against um I hope I haven't misstated
that I'd be happy to produce the email
and forward it on to any of the council
members but
um certainly I understand that there are
different opinions in the neighborhoods
for sure thank you Miss Johnson I would
then only ask that we submit this letter
of support uh to the agenda or to the
journal uh for public information
the letter from the daycare yes yes okay
it will be included in the journal thank
you y thank you there's no further
lights there was a motion in a second to
approve as amended roll call this vote
will just be on the amendment oh bagely
Harding hug
Johnson Melton yes row Mr President yes
motion pass six to
one motion to approve and a second as
amended roll call bigley Harding hug
Johnson Melton row Mr President yes
motion pass six to
one item 10 in ordinance to reone
property located at 7105 Military Avenue
from GC District to CC District planning
board and planning department recommend
approval public hearing and vote on
number 10 is today proponents please uh
Joe DLS with td2 10836 Old Mill Road
here to answer any questions thank you
any other proponents
today see none any
opponents public hearing closed Joe just
a quick question for you this is in my
district I think just to the west of
tiger Toms on Military AV right correct
and there's are two vacant Lots right
there that you're combining or what's
what's the plan for what we're doing
here yes uh so once it gets um resed um
the plan is to
um it'll still be two lots built will be
arranged differently and then on the
Northern lot uh a Pizza Hut and then the
South lot there's uh no user yet but
we're anticipating like a coffee shop or
some sort of drive-thru okay new
construction or renovation or new
construction uhhuh okay and what do you
figure your timeline is uh not sure okay
next year maybe okay thank you Mr hug
you recognized
Pizza Hut yes is it going to be a sit in
D in Pizza Hut uh yes I think there
it'll be limited seating but that's
they'll be it's not a like a pickup my
neighborhood Pizza Hut
yeah Reading Rainbow program
and is there a
motion I'll second roll call bigley
Hardin hug Johnson Melton yeah row Mr
President yes thank you pass 7 zero
items 11 and 12 can be considered
together for property located northwest
of Skyline Drive and Stanford Street
planning board and planning department
recommend approval items 11 and 12 are
ordinances to reone this property from
Dr district and R4 District to Dr
district and R4 District public hearing
and vote on items 11 and 12 are today
proponents
please see none any opponents
public hearings
closed a motion a second to approve roll
call Bagley Harding hug Johnson Melton
yeah row Mr President yes motion pass 7
to zero items 13 through 15 can be
considered together for property located
south of 18th and Willis Avenue planning
board and planning department recommend
approval item 13 an ordinance to reone
this property from GC district and R4
District to R7 District item 14 an
ordinance to approve a Pur overlay
District item 15 an ordinance to approve
an amendment to the Future land use
element of the city's master plan to
high density residential public hearing
and vote on items 13 14 and 15 are today
proponents
please is it possible to get this
activated yeah just push it all the way
up there then it should come
on uh good afternoon Jak hoppy 301 South
57th Street Omaha
Nebraska um very Focus the top there if
you want
oh pretty
nice uh very excited to be here before
you today on a a project that we've been
working on for uh 12 months now or a bit
longer um and it's a a transformative
project in it's sort of the 16th and
berett area of North Omaha uh and the
proposal is to
acquire um Chambers Court which is is
currently owned by Omaha Housing
Authority preserve that as affordable
housing and add both additional
affordable and market rate housing in
the surrounding area as well as um as
well as work to come up with a unique
use for the historic garage that's
associated with the project so it's kind
of before you today we'll walk through
both a little bit about process because
I think that's worth commenting on and
then uh and then the near-term
development that'll that'll take place
in stages just so you have the entirety
of the
context uh to start hoppy development is
we're an affordable housing developer
we're based in Lincoln uh this will be
our first project in Omaha we have uh
another project in pilion we develop
three to 400 units a year utilizing a
variety of different affordable housing
structures and resources to try and
deliver to community needs as we
understand them we had an ongoing
discussion with the housing authority of
about some other properties and they
asked us to look at Chambers Court which
was uh a property that was in need had
had previously been renovated in around
2005 and was in need of substantial
additional investment uh and they didn't
have the structure to be able to make
that investment we started looking at
the original property which is in blue
here and a couple of things that that
immediately came up is there's a large
amount of vacant land surrounding the
property and and um and the property
comes with a unique asset which is this
garage and so we started thinking a
little more broadly about what could be
done here and it really started I mean
from there kind of a process of
Engagement with some members of the
community councilwoman Johnson I think
it was maybe a year ago almost next week
that we first sat down with s to talk
about General ideas of of what should
guide us as we thought about the project
um a few of those things are here
ensuring strong neighbor and Resident
engagement and a true concern in the
community for the current residents to
be able to maintain and stay on the
property if that's the path that they
wanted uh there's a lot of discussion
about not just continuing to build
affordable housing in North Omaha but
what could we do in addition to the
affordable housing that might present a
more mixed income
scenario uh finding a pathway to benefit
the North Omaha Community either through
section three or uh some of what we'll
talk about today is is a pretty unique
partnership we've created with another
developer uh bringing back a commercial
sensibility to 16th Street there's been
a significant investment on 16th Street
it formerly was commercial so how could
we help kind of bring that sense of
community planning where that was felt
like more of a commercial
area uh examine the ability to do more
with a community benefit how we might
use some of the space and then a big one
was continue to honor uh Senator Ernie
chambers that that this was really seen
as as a as an opportunity for the
community to honor him and his
legacy and we've kind of broken it up
into four sections and the reason we're
applying uh now uh is really because
we're submitting our tax credit
application for the Redevelopment of
kind of the anchoring portion of the
project was which is the preservation of
Chambers Court as affordable housing and
adding 60 new affordable housing units
in the vacant land around it so we're
submitting that application shortly
that's kind of why you see us maybe in
advance of of of some of the work that
we'll do but we also have the 18th
Street um the west side of 18th Street
which we're holding uh and will continue
to hold for the purpose of doing a
market rate development so that when all
told we'll have about 200 units of
housing between the affordable and the
market rate in really kind of a mixed
income
scenario um we're also uh entitling
today 1628 berett street that is not a
project that we are going to do uh it's
a project that uh Don Curry who's
another developer who's focused a lot of
efforts on North Omaha he's going to
take that forward for efficiency's sake
and because of uh some of the way that
the land laid out we traded one of our
sites for one of his uh and agreed to
entitle his portion to make it easier
for him to move forward with his
development process and then lastly
we'll retain the historic garage and
we're looking to renovate that into a a
community amenity space um we have a
couple of conversations ongoing it's a
truly unique facility and and we're
optimistic that we'll be able to find a
really great use
there so just to give you the map
everything in green that you see here is
part of the initial anchoring tax credit
application so that again is 130 units
all affordable through the low-income
housing tax credit program the blue is
the the area that we are retaining for a
market rate portion to go alongside that
um the the dark blue the light blue is
the lot uh that Mr Curry will move
forward with and then the yellow is uh
what's currently being used or the the
historic garage it's currently being
used just as a um well really a parking
garage for Omaha Housing Authority but
we hope to find a use and renovate for a
broader uh better
purpose we have a few folks who really
partnered with us after the initial
conversations around some of the
aspirations that this development should
have and trying and adhere to we did a
much more targeted discussion with the
existing residents and the surrounding
residents in the uh two or three block
area so we had a couple of community
meetings supported by neighborhood
canvasing really to collect the feedback
of the folks who live there to help set
priorities and aspirations of the
development specifically to Chambers
Court basically asking them what is it
that we should invest in here if we're
going to try and transform this
apologize that you can't read it very
well uh there is a big focus on safety
and access there's a lot of people who
are moving through the property now who
don't live there there are laundry rooms
in the basement we intend to address all
of those issues and and be able to focus
a little bit more on security um
accessibility it's it's a beautiful
historic uh building set of buildings
they are not handicap accessible so it's
a challenge for a lot of the res res uh
in the new construction that we're
putting in uh we will address that
um uh Transportation playground and that
sense of commercial sensibility were all
also things that were brought up and
that we intend to address and I have
some of the team members who focused on
some of this input Gathering who join me
here
today so again just uh just because this
is the most near term of the set of
actions that we're going to take is the
Chambers Court Redevelopment it's going
to be 131 units in totality between 70
original and 61 new one to four bedrooms
uh an additional benefit of the of the
buildings itself is that they present
they're much larger uh three and four
bedrooms than typically are done in
affordable housing today so it serves a
unique need in the community that needs
to be
preserved uh we're utilizing historic
tax credits and it's it's in a historic
uh easement area so the original
buildings will maintain that existing
look and feel um we're using the 4% uh
low-income housing tax credit Bond
program such that all the units will be
targeted at 60% meean income for this
anchoring
development uh and then really we're
underwriting the rents to uh maintain
the current level of affordability for
the Omaha Housing Authority tenants who
are able to stay at the property so
it'll be they won't or don't anticipate
them having a change in their rental
scenario and we can do a renovation
where we aren't going to be displacing
any residents we can do what's called a
renovation in place where if they some
will choose to move because they uh this
will no longer be owned by the Housing
Authority so they will no longer be
classified as Housing Authority tenants
and some for some people that will
probably be preferred uh but for those
that prefer to stay at the property
we're committed to finding a pathway for
them to do that uh we get to put some
fun new amenities um in the in the new
construction portion will have a
community room washer dryer uh a safe
modern washer dryer area and a leasing
office that'll be on 16th Street we
intend to also address the playground
right now it's uh kind of the what I
would call is bare minimum of a
playground and we think there's
opportunity to enhance that to make the
green space uh more
usable and then because we're increasing
the scale of the entirety of the project
uh what that really allows us to do in
why we were really interested in it is
be it allows us to have on-site
management uh and leasing office that's
staffed that's really around safety and
ensuring that residents are being
responded to that we're understanding if
a door is propped open or left open uh
and that we've got sort of eyes on the
street just like a
um uh what you a front porch sort of
scenario it will be able to have staff
that's there all the time right now
because 70 units is a hard scale to
manage with on-site management and
that's really why uh the Housing
Authority isn't doing that
now
um and just uh from a timeline
perspective this always critical uh you
know we we really started this in Q4 of
last year Q one of this year with
initial discussions in the community uh
we moved that into uh sort of a refining
of our concept and direct engagement
with the residents in the
community um we at that time were
designing and aggregating some of the
sites so in June uh the city voted to
sell us some of their Surplus land in
that area we did some other work to
aggregate some of the different sites uh
today before you we're going through the
the entitlement process and on Monday my
the rest of my team is working hard on
the tax credit application that will be
submitted we'll receive our bond credit
allocation in the q1 of next year we'll
probably also be bringing forward a tiff
application around that time or maybe
just before so we do intend to pursue
tax increment financing for this uh and
then in next summer is when we will have
our closing and construction start and
it's probably around a year-long process
uh to get the initial work renovated and
maybe a little bit longer to get the new
construction completed so we're well in
advance of of kind of when the residents
will be impacted but we intend to
communicate openly and have thus far uh
as to our intentions
I'm happy to take any questions um I
also we do have um Mr Hayes and Miss
donack who led our community engagement
here uh as well as Mr Curry uh so if
there's any questions around sort of the
broader uh context of what we're doing
happy to respond great thank you thanks
for that
overview any other proponents that want
to speak today
hello everyone happy holiday so I'm
actually uh very adamant and happy about
this project I think you all know know
that I've been a uh a big proponent of
16th Street just from the standpoint of
my connection there you know spending
time off of 16th and em and currently
what I'm doing now off of a 16th and em
and we've uh gotten to the point to
where we're framing the first floor for
our 16th and Spencer and then our third
development would be 16th and W the 16th
and birat was going to be our fourth so
I guess I pretty much purchased at the
right area in reference to the berc
corridor and I'll I'll end with this I
mean you know again I've been a big
proponent of 16th Street just from the
standpoint of if we were in Chicago or
New York you able to walk out of your
front door and see the Skyland of the
city it's Prime real estate and I really
do believe that that 16th Street
Corridor is going to uh pretty much um
be a nice area that we can really see
some mixed income development taking
place in over the next years thanks and
Don just your name and address for the
sorry uh Don Curry address is 3324 North
16th Street uh talented 10th group
development thanks thank you any other
proponents that want to
speak hello Dewan Lamont Hayes 4362 sew
Street Omaha Nebraska um I was a part of
the engagement team um doing a lot of uh
we contracted with Sparks CDI um and
conducted two weeks of walking around
the neighborhood going door too speaking
to people at our new chambers's courts
as well as the surrounding houses and
providing information and flyers to um
neighbors so that they could come to a
meeting that was on 16th Street uh we
closed 16th Street and held it there for
visibility um and we were able to hear
directly from residents what their
concerns were um a lot of it doing in
regards to safety as especially spaces
and access for children um and then you
know Transit safety as well um which you
know Metro next and several other
Transportation studies that we have do
indicate that 16th Street is slated for
um improvements there and so you know I
really appreciate hoppy Development
Group and and this team and Don for
really focusing on the affordability
aspect of this and um leading a way in
community engagement uh as and trans
Arcy we have not seen this level of
transparency with a developer in Omaha
to my knowledge or degree so um and the
the um commitment to continue to provide
you know a digital correspondence a
landing page on the website um several
different um opportunities for the
neighbors to be present and many had
never had any engagement with omala
housing authority and so we were able to
host that for them to actually field
questions and be able to direct their
complaints directly to an OA
representative so um you know I I would
say continue to hold developers to this
degree of of transparency and
accountability and to if you see this
President here continue to ask for this
level of Engagement um because this is
what we need to actually ensure that we
have affordable sustainable housing here
in Omaha so thank you thank you any
other proponents today
hey everybody uh Manel cook uh I'm here
with lern nerson uh 14 710 West Dodge
Road um uh I've been uh happy to be
involved with what I think is an
exceptional team and an exceptional
project um and I believe that one of the
first steps to attaining the level of
affordable housing that we want to see
is maintaining what we already have and
I think this project does that and and I
also think that this project helps
secure and maintain a historic site with
a historic name and uh Jake and team
have really set the bar for development
in the area with the engagement like
danan said um and I'm just really
excited to see the positive impact that
this project has uh for the community
and then also the surrounding area
thanks thank you other proponents
hello um my name is Clarice dbec 901
farom Street um I was a part of the team
that led the community outreach and
engagement for this project um and even
more than that I grew up in North Omaha
on 16th in EMT so right down the street
and never in my lifetime um did I
imagine or have even the opportunity to
see a project like this come to my
neighborhood
um and I am super impressed with
developers like Don Curry and like Hoy
development with the level of intention
and Care um that they put into these
projects um and when I heard about it
and I had the opportunity to be involved
I was excited for those reasons um I was
also excited um to
be able to be a part of this development
even if it is in a small way um I'm also
excited to be able to see um what these
new developments the positive changes
that these new developments can lead to
um in my neighborhood especially as a
young professional um who grew up in
North Omaha who lived in North homaha
basically my entire life until recently
knowing that the primary reason why I
left North North Omaha was because there
wasn't the sort of Housing
Development um and Community amenities
and Community spaces that young people
want so if we want young people to stay
in North Omaha if we want to have a um
diverse Community with people coming
from different professions and
backgrounds um we need to have a
diversity of housing type
um a diversity of income um and I think
those are some things that this project
will bring and I look forward to seeing
it completed thank you congratulations
on your recent election to the Metro
Transit
board any other
proponents see none any
opponents public hearing is closed Miss
Johnson you're recognized thank you
first I'd like to thank all of the
individuals that came up and spoke in
favor of this um your words were very um
very rewarding and refreshing because um
those are the things that I've seen
through this development and the
conversations that I've had in
discussions with Jake um looking forward
to this excitement continuing I
understand that it will be about a year
before we see U this becoming reality
but I also want to um say thanks to Jake
um for the um placing such value of
retaining the legacy of Senator
Chambers um the engagement um that you
um brought into the area to ensure that
those um in need um did feel like um
they were being heard their voices were
being heard and their thoughts and the
Sens sensitivity of all of that that
goes into what real Community
involvement
is um I also would like to say that I
appreciate you
explaining um what's going to happen
with the current residents what their
opportunities are whether they could
stay or if they were going to um have to
move because that has been some chatter
in the community so you've you've
cleared that up and I appreciate that in
conclusion I will be supporting this
thank you thank you Mr
Ro thank you Mr President I think
everyone on this board knows that I get
excited when I see an affordable housing
project uh come before us and and this
one is an exciting project and I I just
wanted to take a minute to thank Jake
for taking the risk for uh using your
expertise I mean you are uniquely
qualified to do a project like this with
your background and your experience I've
watched hoppy development work in
affordable housing realm all across the
state with successful projects in
Lincoln and Grand Island um and many
many other communities so I just wanted
to say thank you for coming to Omaha
thank you for taking the risk and thank
you for Lending us your unique abilities
and your team's abilities uh to pull off
a successful project and I just wish you
all
success thank you Jake I might uh have
you come up too and I I'll also offer
you a compliment but I do have one
question for you
yeah and I do want to say um welcome to
Omaha as well um one of the things the
Omaha city council has done from time to
time is meet with the Lincoln City
Council and this goes back a few few
years now but we had a summit in Lincoln
where we met with your father and talked
about hoppy development so I know of all
the great and tradition you have in your
family around these projects and the
great affordable housing progress
they've made in Lincoln in no small part
I think to you and your and your
family's company so I think you've
picked a great first project here in
Omaha we're happy to support with this
today and I agree with council member
Johnson uh you've really shown a
sensitivity to uh Community engagement
and honoring the legacy of this
particular building working with
OHA um in a very thoughtful way which I
think is what we like to see thank you
um and you understand the complexities
of affordable housing which is apparent
in the in the presentation we had there
and the various pieces of funding you've
had to put together to to make this a
reality in those documents you talked
about um the target
population being those with um average
median income of 60% or less in the area
can you give us a number um what you
would expect rents to be for these units
going forward yeah uh ballpark uh one
bedroom might be at at 60% might be
around ,000 a month uh a two-bedroom
might be
$150 the in place rents at Chambers are
lower than that so we anticipate
maintaining those in place rents
consistent with the levels that they are
today um but I think in the end you'll
end up with um with kind of three levels
of affordability when we think of mixed
income we'll have you know some that are
truly market rate that'll be in the
approximate phase we'll have some within
this project itself that are going to be
more at that uh 60% uh level and then
you'll have some that are continuing to
be voucher holders that are we maintain
those units affordable for them as
voucher holders so you really
even in spite of the fact that you know
the first phase will be all uh
technically low income through the
classification from the low income
housing tax credits uh there will still
be a a mix of incomes within the
affordable portion of the project as
well good great thank you and we hope to
up and above this project engage you in
our affordable action housing plan too
and work with you on that abely that'd
be great yeah and then lastly
congratulations you are recently awarded
um recognition by Omaha design I that
event and uh was very well deserved well
I followed some great footsteps of uh Mr
cook over there and some others in the
community so I I really appreciate the
opportunity to kind of Welcome us here
and it is a really cool project we were
super excited to kind of get to Steward
what we consider a significant Legacy
both in the project itself and in the
North Omaha community and we look
forward to bringing it to life great
thank you Mr Begley you're
recognized good afternoon Mr hoppy
um thanks for being here today and for
for the investment you're making I I'm
just curious I think I know the answer
but the experience that hoppy
development has in Lincoln and bringing
that skill set and expertise Omaha
litech getting that that process is that
pretty difficult to navigate is that
fair to say because I've talked to other
developers on the complexities of that
it's a very specific set of knowledge
that I I wish didn't have to be so
specific and that more developers felt
comfortable utilizing but unfortunately
the way it's turned out it is a a unique
skill set I think or one organizes
themselves as a development firm
uniquely around the ability to execute
on the the tax credit housing and I I I
know in in my time on the council I just
haven't heard that from one developer
it's been several yeah so I applaud you
for what you bring to the table for the
community and specifically the the old
Chambers Court location in north omo um
that's just by evident by the
presentation you made here today and
knowing you're standing the community I
I think that's going to be great and I'm
glad to support this and thanks again
for your team for for engaging this
thanks thank you very much thank you Mr
hug I was going to make some smart
remark about Rick hoppy but I won't not
a relation yeah I know but
um hey as you look in the future to
expand your footprint in Omaha I would
encourage you to look real strong in my
district there's plenty of opportunities
a district for and uh you would be more
than welcome in my district thank you
well I look forward to learning more
about those opportunities thank you
thank you there's no fer the lights is
there a
motion there's a motion a second to
approve roll call Bagley Hardin hug John
Melton yes row Mr President yes motion
pass 7 to Zero thanks for your
testimony item 16 and 17 can be
considered together for property located
at 3030 L Street planning board and
planning department recommend approval
item 16 a resolution to approve a
special use permit to allow a daycare in
the hi District item 17 an ordinance to
amend the boundaries of the MCC overlay
District to incorporate this property
into that District public hearing and
vote on items 16 and 17 are today
proponents please
see none any
opponents public hearing is closed Mr
hug motion to
approve there motion a second to approve
roll call bigley Harding hug Johnson
Melton row Mr President yes motion
passed 7 to zero consent agenda any
member of the city council may cause any
item placed on the consent agenda to be
removed items removed from the consent
agenda shall be taken up by the city
Council immediately following the
consent agenda and the order in which
they were removed unless otherwise
provided by the city council Rules of
Order the public hearings on agenda
items 18 and 19 were held on November
19th I don't see any further lights is
there a
motion there's a motion in a second to
approve roll call Bagley Hardin hug
Johnson Melton row Mr President yes
motion pass 7 to
zero the public hearings on agenda items
20 through 38 are to today if you wish
to address the city council regarding
these items please come to the
microphone indicate the agenda item
number you wish to address identify
Yourself by name address and who you
represent and if you are a proponent or
an opponent these are items 20 through
38 see none public hearing is
closed there's a motion a second to
approve these items roll call bigley
Harding hug Johnson Melton row Mr
President yes motion pass 7 to zero item
39 a resolution to approve the
reappointment of Jeremy Aspen to the
zoning board of appeals the public
hearing and vote on number 39 is today
proponents
please see none any
opponents public hearing is
closed there's a motion to approve in a
second roll call bigley Hardin hug
Johnson Melton yes row Mr President yes
motion pass 7 to
zero item 40 an Ordnance to authorize
the issuance of a purchase order to aoka
water Technologies LLC for the purchase
of an 18,000 gallon TurnKey hydrogen
peroxide solution to be utilized at the
Missouri River water resource recovery
facility the public hearing on number 40
is today proponents
please see none any opponents
public hearing is
closed item item 41 in ordinance to
approve a streetcap maintenance
agreement with milor District 1 LLC for
streetscape and Landscape improvements
in the right of way the public hearing
on number 41 is today proponents
please see none any
opponents public hearings closed item 42
an ordinance to approve a land lease
agreement with Verizon Wireless for a
period of five years the public hearing
on number 42 is today proponents
please see none any
opponents public hearing is closed item
43 in ordinance to approve a major
amendment to mix use District
development agreement for Hawthorn Court
located at 17662 Welch Plaza planning
board and planning department recommend
approval the public hearing 43 is today
proponents please yes excuse me Mr
President members of the council L Joven
11440 Weston Road appearing on behalf of
the the applicant lanaha Q
development this is just a major
Amendment to the mixed juice development
agreement this is an existing shopping
center on the uh northeast corner of
180th in Q Street the proposed amendment
affects this particular property right
here which is the last undeveloped lot
in a long-standing shopping center uh
it's a 9,000 multi-tenant Bay building
that they're proposing to
construct and uh it's just the amendment
is to expand some of the uses that are
allowed in this particular mixed use
area so with that I'm happy to answer
any questions that you might have thank
you any other proponents
today seeing none any
opponents public hearing closed item 44
in ordinance to approve the 1501 Howard
and standard rehab tax increment
financing Redevelopment agreement public
hearing on number 44 is today proponents
please uh yeah Don Satan City Planning
here to answer any questions
thank you any other
proponents see none any
opponents public heing closed item 45 in
ordinance to accept the bid of armor
Express for 200 ballistic vest systems
for the Omaha Police Department Public
hearing on number 45 is today proponents
please see none any
opponents public hearing is closed item
46 an ordinance to amend various
sections of chapter 23 of the Omaha
municipal code to approve amendments to
the functional employees group labor
agreement Personnel Board recommends
approval public hearing on number 46 is
today proponents
please I believe we'll get a brief
overview of each of these next items
from um the administration and the
negotiating team good afternoon Annie
Matthews Labor Relations director I'm
here to answer any questions you might
have but I'll turn it over to Mark
McQueen for that presentation thank you
thank you good good afternoon Mark
McQueen Barett Holm 1700 farum Street
Annie and I partnered uh on negotiating
the functional renewal contract pretty
simple there's a couple creative
elements that are noteworthy uh the
intent going into these negotiations was
just to focus on a one-year deal in
order to get the functional uh
bargaining unit on the same contract
renewal schedule as the other civilian
bargaining units they haven't been for a
few years so we wanted a one-year deal
uh
for wages we uh proposed and the
functional group accepted a 2% wage
increase for this one-year deal that's
consistent with the other civilian
groups and that's why we targeted that
amount where we did something a little
bit unusual is in the health savings
account portion of the medical insurance
benefit on in this unit we proposed to
increase in 2025 that health savings
account contribution from the city to
each of the employees individual
accounts $100 increase for those en
enrolled in single coverage and $200 for
those enrolled in non-single coverage
the idea there we're trying to keep up
with the federal standards
for minimum deductibles required or
authorized under those Federal
Regulations so we worked out that
one-year deal and then we uh as Annie
will explain here shortly went to some
of the other civilian bargaining units
and talked about how we might increase
those Health Savings Account
contributions in the Years Beyond
2025 so we agreed to a second increase
in
20126 uh another $100 for the single
enroll e and another $200 for the non-
single enroll EAS and that uh health
savings account contribution would
remain in in effect through uh contract
year 2028 and Annie is going to explain
to you how we did she did the same uh
type of arrangements with the other
bargaining unit
and in exchange for that we won't talk
about health insurance either plan
design or percentage of Premium
contributions or health savings account
contributions uh until after 2028 so it
kind of takes it off the table in a
manner that helps the employees and
helps the city as well the only thing
that I haven't mentioned so far is uh we
adjusted the long longevity pay uh
benefit for the functional group so that
it matched the aec
and the syp group which has been in
place since 2022 so we made that uh
offer retroactive for those employees
who were still currently employed and
who were employed since 2022 so that's
the deal uh the negotiations were
collaborative quick uh very effective uh
the union President Michael Maxon as
always was very professional and very
collaborative in his interaction with us
and I think he's joining us via Zoom
today he couldn't be here in person but
just respect y asking for your support
uh for this renewal agreement okay thank
you any other proponents that want to
speak
today see none any
opponents back heing closed I don't see
any lights next item please item 47 in
ordinance to amend sections 23-42 and
23-43 of the Omaha municipal code to
approve amendments to the simtech labor
agreement personal board recommends
approval public heing on number 47 is
today proponents
please good afternoon Annie Matthews
Labor Relations director with the city
uh Mr McQueen just provided you with a
pretty good summary of what these
healthc care changes are in this
amendment to the simtech labor agreement
um and it'll also apply to our aec
employees um as you might know that's a
non-unionized group but they typically
historically have seen the same benefits
that our simtech employees do receive um
I don't want to be entirely repetitive
but just to summarize um you will see a
2025 increase to the HSA contributions
so a $100 increase for the single
coverage $200 increase for our single
plus one in family coverage um and um
you will see that in 2025 and 2026 there
will be another increase um and that
amount will be locked in for 2027 and
2028 along with that you'll see some
amended language being proposed that
will freeze the premium amount that the
employees will be responsible for
through 202
along with freezing the plan design so
what is covered under the plan is not
going to change for the employees to
through
2028 uh the trade-off here being that
the increase in the city's contribution
in 2025 and again in
2026 um it'll work to Aid um in the
raising cost of healthcare for our
employees but through freezing that
contribution amount through 2028 um the
city's provided some certainty as to
what those HSA contribution costs will
be um and so lastly there's some cleanup
language if you will um based on how the
city determines what the deductible will
be um for single plus one in family
amount each year as determined by the
IRS they set that amount at the
beginning of each year and so there's
some language in there that clarifies
that moving forward so we don't have
that same dispute um but we would ask
for your approval good thank Youk you
any other proponents on number
47 see none any opponents
public hearing is closed next item item
48 an ordinance to approve an amendment
to the local 251 collective bargaining
agreement public hearing on number 48 is
today proponents
please good afternoon Annie Matthews
Labor Relations director um again these
are the same changes that I just
described for Sim tech and aec and then
functional just for our local 251
employees um the effort here is to keep
all of our civilian bargaining groups on
the on the same plan seeing those same
Healthcare benefits so
um same Provisions same changes happy to
answer any questions thank you thank you
for those summaries any other proponents
that want to
speak see none any
opponents public hearing
closed next is non-action
items Mr Harden you're recognized thank
you Mr President um on our non action
items uh agenda item number 62
which is the uh climate action and
resiliency plan uh which is scheduled
for public hearing and vote on our uh
December 10th meeting uh I I I think
that's uh important enough that I'd like
to have the public hearing on December
12th and then have the vote on the 17th
therefore giving uh both the public and
us the opportunity to listen to the the
testimony see if there are any
amendments or any alterations um that
might be made to the the document and uh
rather than do floor amendments I
thought that that would probably be um
in the best interest to to get the the
best product uh of what we've been
working on for for a long time now so um
I guess I would propose that then as an
amendment to item 62 which would be to
have the public hearing on December 10th
2024 and then the vote would be on
December 17
2024 and that yeah that was a motion
okay there's a motion in a
second I don't see any further lights
roll
Bagley Harding yes hug yes Johnson
Melton yes row yes Mr President yes
motion pass 7 to
zero items 49 through 77 do not require
public hearing or city council
consideration at this meeting but will
be placed on a future agenda for public
hearing and or vote the reason for
non-action is noted after the item on
the agenda as well as the date the item
is expected to appear on agenda for
consideration is there a motion to
adjourn motion a second roll call Bagley
Hardin hug Johnson Melton row Mr
President yes motion pass 7 to Zer
meeting is adjourned at
311 thank you